Guide to the Stephen C. Harward Papers, 1949-1975 and undated, bulk 1963-1975 RL.00518
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Stephen C. Harward papers
1949-1975 and undated, bulk 1963-1975
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Harward, S. C. (Stephen Cannada), 1922-1993.
RL.00518
10.5 Linear Feet
Stephen Cannada Harward served on the Durham City School Board for 12 years in the 1960s and 1970s. During this time, the Durham city and county school districts were desegregated following a series of court mandates beginning in 1963. The collection contains memos, bulletins, reports, evaluations, minutes, agendas, educational and administrative guides and handbooks, court documents, financial statements and budgets, correspondence, clippings, printed materials, and maps pertaining to the activity of the Durham City School Board. The papers span the years 1949-1975 and document the daily workings of the Durham City School Board chiefly between the years 1963 and 1975, with a special focus on the process of desegregation during that time. It contains no personal papers of Stephen C. Harward.
Circa 4000 Items
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. There may be a 48-hour delay in obtaining these materials.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Stephen C. Harward Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2003.
Biographical Note
Chronology List
1922 Stephen Cannada Harward born
1960 Actions Wheeler v. Durham City Board of Education and Spaulding v. Durham City Board of Education filed for disestablishment of separate segregated school systems in the Durham city school system
1963 Action Thompson v. Durham County Board of Education filed for desegregation of Durham County Administrative School Unit Wheeler, Spaulding, and Thompson suits consolidated Federal court ordered Durham city schools to adopt freedom-of-choice desegregation plan
1963-1975 Harward served on Durham City School Board
1965 Durham County schools began desegregation under freedom-of-choice plan Elementary and Secondary Education Act passed as part of President Johnson's "War on Poverty"
1966 Court approved Durham City School Board freedom-of-choice plan
1969 Following Green v. School Board of New Kent County and Alexander v. Holmes County Board of Education decisions, the Federal Court of Appeals directed the abandonment of freedom-of-choice plan and the implementation of a geographic zoning plan for desegregation of Durham County schools
1970 The corresponding mandate was made for Durham city schools
1971 Proposed merger of Durham city and county school systems rejected by two-thirds majority
1972-1974 Harward served as Duke University Treasurer
1992 Durham city and county school districts merged into Durham Public School district
1993 Death of Harward
Collection Overview
The Stephen C. Harward Papers span the years 1949-1975, with the bulk of the material dating from 1963-1975. The collection contains approximately 300 files stemming from the activities of the Durham City School Board (North Carolina), including audit reports, budgets, financial records, agendas, external and internal evaluations, teachers' manuals, and education policy materials, as well as court and other documents related to the redistricting and desegregation of the Durham city schools. Beyond the daily workings of the Durham City School Board and the Durham city school system are also materials documenting the use of funds stemming from the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (ESEA), which was later renamed and revised as the No Child Left Behind Act of 2001, and materials related to concerns about student discipline and unrest during the late 1960s. The collection is divided into six series: Desegregation and Redistricting, Financial Papers, Handbooks, Legal Papers, Reports, and Subject Files.
The Desegregation and Redistricting Series collects materials related to the different attempts to desegregate the Durham city schools in response to court mandates. It documents the legal struggle deriving from the NAACP Legal Defense Fund suits of 1959 and 1960, the latter of which continued through the 1970s in response to the outcomes of other suits, particularly Green v. School Board of New Kent County (1968) and Alexander v. Holmes County Board of Education (1969), both of which demanded the abandonment of "freedom-of-choice" integration plans in favor of geographical zoning plans, and Swann v. Charlotte-Mecklenburg Board of Education (1971). Following the latter, the Durham City School Board was given a mandate by the court in 1975 to eliminate racially identifiable schools in the district, using any means necessary to ensure that the balance of black to white students at any school varied no less than 10% from the overall racial balance of the school group. Along with the legal papers, the series documents the move to desegregate the Durham city schools with memos and internal school board documents, clippings, correspondence from parents, maps, proposals (in both draft and completed form), and a printed booklet about desegregation. It also deals with the related attempts to merge the city and county school districts into a single unit, finally accomplished in 1992. The Financial Papers Series houses budgets, financial statements, accounting materials, and other papers documenting the financial workings of the Durham city schools and school board. Those interested in these finances should also consult the extensive audit reports in the Reports Series. The Handbooks Series documents educational and administrative practices and concerns of the time with teachers' manuals and handbooks, student and administrative handbooks, policy statements, school directories, and bound print materials on educational topics. The small Legal Papers Series contains the legal files not related to the desegregation suits, including court papers, bills passed, and easements on school properties. The Reports Series collects audit reports, external and internal evaluations of schools and school programs, and results of studies and surveys. These documents contain detailed information related to the ESEA funds and their usage (in the audit reports and several narrative evaluations). Finally, the Subject Files Series contains topical files documenting different projects, programs, initiatives, and issues addressed by the Durham City School Board. It also documents the regular functioning of the school board in the extensive files of meeting minutes, agendas, and information bulletins.
Related Material
Those interested in the history of the Durham City School Board and the desegregation of Durham schools may wish to consult the Nicholas Rencher Harris Papers and the Women-in-Action for the Prevention of Violence and Its Causes, Inc., Durham Chapter, Records, also housed at the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library. Nicholas Rencher Harris (1900-1965) was an African-American businessman and civic leader in Durham and served on the Durham Board of Education during the late 1950s and early 1960s; that collection also houses materials related to school desegregation in Durham. The Durham chapter of Women-in-Action for the Prevention of Violence and Its Causes was founded by Elna Spaulding in 1968, and the organization was involved in the struggle for school integration in the 1970s. These collections, both cataloged separately from the Stephen C. Harward Papers, are searchable by title in the Duke University Libraries online catalog.
Durham (N.C.) -- Race relations; Durham (N.C.) -- History; School districts -- North Carolina -- Durham County; Schools -- Centralization -- North Carolina -- Durham County; Education -- Southern States; School integration -- North Carolina -- Durham; Public Schools -- North Carolina -- Durham -- History; Public Schools -- North Carolina -- Durham -- Finance; School districts -- North Carolina -- Evaluation; School improvement programs -- United States; Public Schools -- North Carolina -- Durham; Public Schools -- North Carolina -- Durham -- Business management -- Auditing; Segregation in education -- Law and legislation -- United States; Discrimination in education -- Law and legislation -- United States; Federal aid to education -- United States; Student movements -- United States -- History -- 20th century; Urban schools -- North Carolina -- Durham; Public Schools -- North Carolina -- Durham -- Handbooks, manuals, etc.; Education -- North Carolina -- Durham; Harward, S. C. (Stephen Cannada), 1922-1993.; Harward, S. C. (Stephen Cannada), 1922-1993.
- Desegregation and Redistricting Series, 1959-1975, 3 boxes
  Scope and Contents note
  Houses materials related to the desegregation of the Durham, N.C. city schools, proposed redistricting, and the repeated failed attempts to consolidate the city and county administrative units into a single school district (accomplished in 1992). Formats include memos and internal school board documents, clippings, correspondence from parents, legal files and briefs, study and survey reports, maps, proposals (in both draft and completed form), and a printed booklet. The extensive court files mostly pertain to the NAACP suit of Wheeler, Spaulding, and Thompson v. the Durham City and County School Boards, begun in 1960 and continuing on through 1975; they are of particular interest in documenting the various court mandates and school board proposals for desegregation plans. The later court papers (from 1974 and 1975) contain useful summaries of the process of desegregation, as well as progress reports and statistics gathered by the school board and submitted to the court. Researchers interested in the attempted merger of the city and county schools may wish to consult the files on the bond issues of 1967-1973 in the Subject Files Series, which contain some related materials. Those interested in federal financial support for desegregation may also wish to consult the files on the Emergency School Aid Act of 1972.
  Arranged in alphabetical order by folder title.
  - Brief on outside school district but inside city limits, 1971 (Box 1A)
  - Civil Rights Act compliance, 1965 (Box 1A)
  - Civil rights survey, 1974 (Box 1A)
  - Charlotte plan, 1974 (Box 1A)
  - Class assignment plans, 1974 (Box 1A)
  - Consolidation of city and county schools, 1968-1969, 2 folders (Box 1A)
  - Consolidation study I, 1968 (Box 1A)
  - Consolidation study II, 1966 (Box 1A)
  - Desegregation: Opportunity or Problem, 1970 (Box 1A)
  - Desegregation suits, 1959-1962; 4 folders (Box 1A)
  - Desegregation suits, 1963-1965; 3 folders (Box 1B)
  - Desegregation suits, 1966-1975, 7 folders (Box 2)
  - Emergency School Aid Act, 1974-1975 (Box 2)
  - Emergency School Aid Act--application for assistance, 1973-1975 (Box 2)
  - Enrollment, 1970-1974 (Box 2)
  - Maps, 1964, 1970-1974 (Box 2)
  - Merger, 1971, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous, 1964-1970 (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous, 1974-1975, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Proposed redistricting, Durham city schools--junior high schools, 1972-1974 (Box 3)
  - RTI attendance zones, 1964-1970 (Box 3)
- Financial Papers Series, 1961-1975, 2 boxes
  Primarily budgets and financial statements of the Durham city school system, but also information on accounting, wages, employee insurance, and real estate appraisals. Researchers interested in the finances of the city school district should also consult the audit reports located in the Reports Series.
  Arrangement note
  Arranged alphabetically, then chronologically by date.
  - Accounting system, 1968 (Box 3)
  - Appraisal of real estate: Southside, Crest Street, and Edgemont Elementary Schools, 1972 Aug. 18 (Box 3)
  - Budget, 1961-1966, 5 folders (Box 3)
  - Budget, 1966-1975, 7 folders (Box 4)
  - Budget--special, 1967-1969 (Box 4)
  - Current expenditures by source of funds, 1966-1968, 3 folders (Box 4)
  - Financial statements, 1969-1974, 6 folders (Box 5)
  - Insurance, 1975 (Box 5)
  - Salaries, wages, 1969-1975 (Box 5)
- Handbooks Series, 1949-1975 and undated, bulk 1962-1975, 2 boxes
  Comprises educational manuals; handbooks for students, teachers, and administrators; food service guides; school law reference books; and other books and pamphlets treating topics related to education.
  - Activity manual-- F.O.O.D. For Thought: Focus on Optimal Development, Intermediate Level, 1974 (Box 5)
  - Activity manual-- F.O.O.D. For Thought: Focus on Optimal Development, Primary Level, 1974 (Box 5)
  - Athletics manual, junior high school, 1974 (Box 5)
  - Board of Education policy manual, 1975, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Bridging the Gap between Government in Books and Government in Action by Albert Coates, 1974 (Box 5)
  - Career Opportunities Program overview, circa 1971 (Box 5)
  - Coaches manual, Durham city schools, undated (Box 5)
  - Cooperative Distributive Education student handbook, undated (Box 5)
  - Discipline Problems: An Educational Malignancy by Walter E. McPhie, 1971 (Box 5)
  - Drugs in North Carolina: Problems and Programs by Anthony D. M. Mulvihill, 1972 (Box 5)
  - Food service guides, 1967-1968 (Box 5)
  - Handbooks for North Carolina school board members, 1962, 1974, 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Hillside High School handbook, 1972 (Box 6)
  - How Can the American People be Given a Better Understanding of Our Economic System?, 1949 (Box 6)
  - The Informer [Durham High School handbook], 1974-1975 (Box 6)
  - Manuals of position descriptions, undated, 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Personnel guide for teachers, 1973 (Box 6)
  - Physical education manual, junior and senior high schools, 1973 (Box 6)
  - Program of studies, Durham High School, 1974 (Box 6)
  - Public Education by Robert E. Phay, undated (Box 6)
  - Public School Laws of North Carolina, 1969 (Box 6)
  - Public School Laws of North Carolina, 1971 (Box 6)
  - School personnel directories, 1966-1975 (Box 6)
  - The Scope and Sources of School Board Authority to Regulate Student Conduct and Status by Stephen R. Goldstein, 1969 (Box 6)
  - Student Rights in North Carolina, 1974 (Box 6)
- Legal Papers Series, 1971-1975, 1 box
  This series contains the legal papers related to Durham city schools and the Durham City School Board not subsumed under the Desegregation and Redistricting Series (which houses all of the court documents and legal papers from the NAACP desegregation suits). This includes bills proposed and passed, easements on school properties, and court papers from a suit ( Ronald Kelly et als v. Lew W. Hannnen et als) made regarding the refusal of Durham High School to allow distribution of the off-campus publication Uprising on campus.
  Arranged alphabetically.
  - Easements, 1975 (Box 6)
  - Federal suit on Uprising, 1971 (Box 6)
  - General Assembly of North Carolina bills, 1973-1975, 2 folders (Box 6)
  - School Budget and Fiscal Control Act, bills proposed, 1975 (Box 6)
- Reports Series, 1959-1975, 5 boxes
  The majority of the series is made up of annual audit reports of the Durham city school system (including correspondence from the firm conducting the audits), but narrative evaluations and quantitative survey and study results are also included. There are also files from individual school evaluations made in 1965, and files of analyses of these evaluations.
  Arranged alphabetically, then chronologically. The one exception to this is the extensive group of audit reports, which are arranged alphabetically by type (audit reports), then date, then report title. This preserves the original organization of the reports in the collection.
  - Audit report correspondence from Ricca, Nelson and Gantt, 1967-1975 (Box 7)
  - Audit reports
    - 1963 June 30
      - Activity funds (Box 7)
      - Cafeteria system (Box 7)
      - Durham city schools (Box 7)
      - Special funds (Box 7)
    - 1964 June 30
      - Activity funds (Box 7)
      - Cafeteria system (Box 7)
      - General fund (Box 7)
      - Miscellaneous funds (Box 7)
    - 1965 June 30
      - Activity funds (Box 7)
      - Cafeteria system (Box 7)
      - General fund (Box 7)
      - Miscellaneous funds (Box 7)
    - 1966 June 30
      - Activity funds (Box 7)
      - ESEA Title I (Box 7)
      - ESEA Title II (Box 7)
      - Food service department (Box 7)
      - General fund (Box 7)
      - Miscellaneous funds (Box 7)
  - Audit reports (Box 8)
    - 1967 June 30
      - Activity funds (Box 8)
      - Durham city schools (Box 8)
      - ESEA Title I (Box 8)
      - ESEA Title II (Box 8)
      - Food service department (Box 8)
      - Miscellaneous funds (Box 8)
    - 1968 June 30
      - Activity funds (Box 8)
      - Durham city schools (Box 8)
      - ESEA Title I (Box 8)
      - ESEA Title II (Box 8)
      - Food service department (Box 8)
      - Miscellaneous funds (Box 8)
    - 1969 June 30
      - Activity funds (Box 8)
      - ESEA Title I (Box 8)
      - ESEA Title II (Box 8)
      - ESEA Title III (Box 8)
      - ESEA Title IV-A (Box 8)
      - Food service department (Box 8)
      - Local current expense and capital outlay fund (Box 8)
      - Special funds (Box 8)
    - 1969 July 15
      - ESEA Title III (Box 8)
    - 1970 June 30
      - Activity funds (Box 8)
      - Federal funds (Box 8)
  - Audit reports (Box 9)
    - 1970 June 30
      - Local funds (Box 9)
    - 1971 June 30
      - Activity funds (Box 9)
      - Federal funds (Box 9)
      - Local funds (Box 9)
    - 1972 June 30
      - Activity funds (Box 9)
      - Federal funds (Box 9)
      - Local funds (Box 9)
    - 1973 June 30
      - Activity funds (Box 9)
      - Federal funds (Box 9)
      - Local funds (Box 9)
    - 1974 June 30
      - Activity funds (Box 9)
      - Federal funds (Box 9)
      - Local funds (Box 9)
    - 1975 June 30
      - Activity funds (Box 9)
      - Federal funds (Box 9)
      - Local funds (Box 9)
  - Charrette reports, 1971 (Box 10A)
  - A Child Well Taught: A Report of the Governor's Study Commission on the Public School System of North Carolina, 1968, 2 folders (Box 10A)
  - Data reports
    - ESEA survey, 1975 Mar. (Box 10A)
    - ESEA Title III statistical data, 1967 Dec. 20 (Box 10A)
  - Durham Chamber of Commerce Subcommittee on Funding of Public Education report, 1972 Sept. (Box 10A)
  - Durham city schools self-study report, 1974 Apr. (Box 10A)
  - Evaluation reports
    - Emergency School Assistance Program, 1971 Oct. (Box 10A)
    - ESEA Title 1, 1966-1967, 1969 (3 reports), 5 reports (Box 10A)
    - ESEA Title 1, 1970-1971, 1975 (2 reports) (Box 10B)
    - SEED evaluation, 1973 June (Box 10B)
  - Government: A Report on City and County, 1970 Summer (Box 10B)
  - How Students Feel About School: A Survey of Student Attitudes at Durham and Hillside High Schools, 1974 July (Box 10B)
  - Local Plan for Occupational Education, 1974 (Box 11)
  - Merit Rating research bulletin, 1959 Oct. (Box 11)
  - Ranking of school administrative units, 1968 July (Box 11)
  - Recommended personnel classification and pay plan, 1973 Sept. (Box 11)
  - Salaries and Supplemental School Taxes research bulletin, 1967 Oct. (Box 11)
  - School reports
    - Brogden Junior High School, 1965 (Box 11)
    - Carr Junior High School, 1965 (Box 11)
    - Durham High School, 1965 (Box 11)
    - Hillside High School, 1965 (Box 11)
    - Holton Junior High School, 1965 (Box 11)
    - Witted Junior High School, 1965 (Box 11)
    - Committee on Accreditation report on 1965 school reports, 1966-1968, 4 folders (Box 11)
  - School survey, 1969 (Box 11)
  - School utilization report, 1975 (Box 11)
  - Students out of School: Dropouts or Pushouts?, 1974 July (Box 11)
- Subject Files Series, 1959-1975 and undated, bulk 1967-1975, 5 boxes
  Topical files Harward kept related to the workings of the school board. Includes proposals, meeting records, correspondence, some financial records (particularly those related to school food service), policy statements, clippings, and pamphlets. Of particular interest for documenting the ongoing workings of and issues faced by the Durham City School Board are the extensive files of meeting agendas, minutes, and information bulletins. Those interested in the attempts to merge the city and county school districts will find relevant information in the folders on the bond issues of various years, as well as the more extensive materials contained in the Desgregation and Redistricting Series.
  - Ability grouping, 1974 (Box 12)
  - Abstract--Durham schools study, 1969-1971 (Box 12)
  - Ad hoc committee on student affairs, 1972 (Box 12)
  - Advisory committee, 1974 (Box 12)
  - Agendas, 1970-1975 (Box 12)
  - Athletic program, 1969-1975 (Box 12)
  - Bids, 1975 (Box 12)
  - Black studies, undated (Box 12)
  - Bond issue, 1967, 1971-1973, 6 folders (Box 12)
  - Book policies, 1969 (Box 12)
  - Calendar, 1970-1975 (Box 12)
  - City-county school commission, 1972-1973 (Box 12)
  - Cooperative School for Pregnant School Girls, 1975 (Box 12)
  - Construction, 1975 (Box 12)
  - Correspondence, 1969-1975 (Box 12)
  - Crest school correspondence, 1972 (Box 12)
  - D.C.E.A. [ Durham City Education Association], 1967-1969 (Box 12)
  - Durham city schools aims--mission, 1973-1974 (Box 13)
  - Durham County Library, 1968 (Box 13)
  - Education Development Council, 1972 (Box 13)
  - Evaluation of the Duke-Walltown tutoring program, 1972 (Box 13)
  - Exceptional children evaluation, 1974 (Box 13)
  - Food service, 1966-1975, 2 folders (Box 13)
  - Green Circle program, 1971 (Box 13)
  - Health benefits program, 1973 (Box 13)
  - Holidays, 1972-1973 (Box 13)
  - Information bulletins, 1969-1973, 4 folders (Box 13)
  - Information bulletins, 1974-1975, 2 folders (Box 14)
  - Joint committee, 1959-1960, 1967 (Box 14)
  - League of Women Voters, 1971 (Box 14)
  - Minutes, 1967-1973, 6 folders (Box 14)
  - Minutes, 1974-1975, 3 folders (Box 15)
  - Miscellaneous, 1975 (Box 15)
  - Miscellaneous information, 1969-1975, 3 folders (Box 15)
  - Miscellaneous proposals, reports, recommendations, suggestions, etc., 1970-1975 (Box 15)
  - Model for an assistant or an associate superintendent's contract, undated (Box 16)
  - National Workshop for Management on Collective Negotiations in Education, 1972 (Box 16)
  - Newsletters, school papers, etc., 1972-1974 (Box 16)
  - Night school, 1975 (Box 16)
  - Property, 1972-1973 (Box 16)
  - Reading tests, 1971-1975 (Box 16)
  - Rules and regulations, 1973 (Box 16)
  - Sale of property, 1973-1975 (Box 16)
  - School Law Bulletin, 1971-1975 (Box 16)
  - Sick leave and substitute teacher regulations, 1972 (Box 16)
  - Statistics, 1968 (Box 16)
  - Southside school property, 1975 (Box 16)
  - Student conduct, 1968-1969 (Box 16)
  - Subcommittee on closing schools, 1974 (Box 16)
  - Suspension of students, etc., 1974-1975 (Box 16)
  - Washington Fastreport, 1972-1973 (Box 16)
- Oversize Materials, 1 oversize folder
  - Desgregation and Redistricting Series, 1972
    - Maps, 1972 (Oversize-folder 1)